Finding Aid for St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church, Ann Arbor, Mich., Records, 1953-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church, Ann Arbor, Mich., Records 1953-1991
St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
3.5 linear feet
86891 Ba 2
Ann Arbor, Michigan Episcopal Church; The record group includes administrative files; newsletters; clippings, and visual materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was deposited by the church (donor no. 7158 ) in 1985. Periodic additions have been made.
The record group is open to research.
St. Clare's began as a mission of St. Andrew's Episcopal Church in 1953. Holding their first services at the old Stone School, the membership steadily grew necessitating the building of their own sanctuary completed in the winter of 1956. In 1974, the members of St. Clare agreed to joint ownership and shared use of the sanctuary and classrooms with Temple Beth-Emeth, a Reform Jewish assemblage. Under the corporate name, Genesis of Ann Arbor, each congregation would share in the management of the facilities, while maintaining its own religious program. This was the first instance of a joint ownership of a house of worship by a church and synagogue in the world. The Genesis Corporation was run by a board made up of representatives of both congregations, with the clergy of each having veto power over the appointment of new clergy to the other.
Church chronology
1953 Mission began as St. Francis of Assisi on land donated by Dr. Inez Wisdom. Name change to St Clare in July. Reverend Philip L. Schenk first vicar.
1956 First service conducted in new building
1957 Reverend Albert Neilson becomes vicar
1963 Reverend Colin Campbell, Jr. becomes rector in June.
1967 St. Clare's obtains parish status
1968 Articles of Incorporation of St. Clare of Assisi
1969 Addition dedicated
1970 St. Clare's renting space to Temple Beth-Emeth
1971 First Peace Seder with both congregations
1972 Douglas Evett becomes rector
1973 Sale of one-half interest in property to Temple Beth-Emeth
1973 Formation of Genesis of Ann Arbor as holding company
1977 Anderson House and property annexed to the city
1878 Dedication of new religious education center addition
The records of St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church consists of annual reports, minutes of vestry (Bishop's Committee) meetings, treasurer's reports, Altar Guild reports, correspondence, bylaws, membership lists, building committee reports, building specifications and construction plans, newsletters, clippings, photographs, and parochial reports.
The record group has been divided into eight series: Administrative and General Records; Newsletters; Genesis Records, Building Committee, Dr. Inez Wisdom file; Clippings, Visual Materials, and Later Records.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Episcopal Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Genesis Corporation (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Interdenominational cooperation.; St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Anderson House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Episcopal Church--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Religious services--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; St. Clare of Assisi Episcopal Church (Ann Arbor, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Videotapes.
- Administrative and General Records 1953-1979
  - Annual reports
    (see also box 4)
    - 1954-1970 (incomplete) (Box 1)
    - 1971-1979 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers
    - Bylaws of St. Clare's (Box 1)
    - Goals statement 1972 (Box 1)
    - Membership lists 1953-1976 (incomplete)\Motions and decisions, 1953-1963 (on index cards) (Box 1)
  - Chronological files 1953-1979
    (includes minutes, treasurer's reports, and correspondence)
    - 1953-1970, 18 folders (Box 1)
    - 1971 (Box 1)
      (includes first discussion of Temple Beth-Emeth joint purchase of church building)
    - 1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973 (Box 2)
      (includes resolution supporting ordination of women)
    - 1974 (Box 2)
      (includes material on acceptability of joint building ownership with Temple Beth-Emeth)
    - 1975-1979, 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Altar Guild reports and membership lists 1957-1984 (Box 2)
  - Women of St. Clare reports 1969-1974 (Box 2)
  - Parochial reports 1954-1979 (incomplete) (Box 2)
  - Registry of church services 1941-1973, 2 volumes (Box 2)
- Newsletters, Bulletins, and Other Publications
  - St. Andrew's Bulletin, 1953-1956 (Box 2)
    (only issues mentioning St. Clare's)
  - St. Andrew's Cross Currents, 1962-1964 (Box 2)
  - St. Clare's Bulletin, 1956-1967 (incomplete), 2 folders (Box 2)
  - St. Clarian, April 1967-1975, 9 folders (Box 2)
  - Ordination ceremony booklets (Box 2)
- Genesis Records 1974-1984
  - Administrative papers 1974-1979 (Box 3)
    (includes articles of incorporation and bylaws)
  - Dedication ceremony 1975 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1976-1978 (Box 3)
    (includes ground-breaking and dedication of additions; Ars Musica)
  - Haggadahs 1971-1979 (Box 3)
    (prayer books from jointly sponsored seders with Temple Beth-Emeth)
  - Clippings 1974-1984 (Box 3)
- Building Committee
  - Building specifications and ground-breaking (Box 3)
  - Building committee reports 1962-1969, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Building specifications 1967 (Box 3)
  - Annexation by Ann Arbor 1973 (Box 3)
  - Architectural drawings (Box 3)
- Dr. Inez Wisdom
  - Correspondence and information on chapel (Box 3)
  - St. Francis chapel (clippings) (Box 3)
  - Anderson House (Box 3)
    (includes clippings)
- Clippings
  - 1953-1973, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Visual Materials
  - Photographs
    - 1953-1956 (Box 3)
    - 1955-1959 (Box 3)
    - 1960-1968 (Box 3)
    - 1968-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1973 20th anniversary picnic (Box 3)
    - Genesis activities 1974-1977 (Box 3)
    - Wisdom/Anderson House (Box 3)
    - Chapel (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Videotape
    - 1994 dedication and consecration of new church (Box 3)
- Later Records
  - Annual Reports 1980, 1983 (Box 4)
  - Vestry minutes and related 1979-1980 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence and related papers 1980-1981, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Sunday bulletins 1975-1982, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - St. Clarian, 1977-1982, 1991, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Capital campaign 1992 (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous 1961-1982 (Box 4)